THE FAMILIAR OF ZERO VOL.14
（《零之使魔》第14集）
Look what we have here.
哎呀…
Takafumi brought a naughty book to school!
敬文同學帶A書來學校
It's not naughty.
這不是A書
Let me see it!
借我看啦
-Stop it! -Naughty, naughty!
-住手 -A書…
Oh, no. Kacchan is picking on Takafumi.
阿勝又盯上敬文了
He's done for.
他完蛋了
All the illustrations are of women.
插圖都是女的
I knew it was dirty.
果然是A書
-It's dirty. -No, it's not.
-好A哦 -不是啦
-How naughty. -It's just a fantasy light novel.
-色胚 -這是奇幻輕小說
"It's just a 'panda-sy tight' novel."
“這素奇飯輕小鎖”
That was spot-on!
你學得好像哦
Give me the naughty book.
有A書？給我拿來
Ms. Fujimiya.
藤宮大…
THE FAMILIAR OF ZERO VOL.14 AQUILEIA'S SAINT
（《零之使魔》第14集 水都市的聖女）
BY NOBORU YAMAGUCHI
（作者，山口昇）
You call this explicit?
你們說這是A書？
You aren't a toddler anymore.
你們是幾歲的小鬼啊？
-Run! -Kacchan is finished.
-快逃吧 -阿勝玩完了呢
I'm sorry, Ms. Fujimiya.
對不起，藤宮大人
Fujimiya, you are so impressive.
藤宮好帥哦
Right? That's my Fujimiya.
對吧？不愧是藤宮
You scared Kacchan to death.
阿勝超害怕的
UNCLE: YOU'RE FINE THE WAY YOU ARE
（舅舅：妳這樣很好啊）
GET HOME
（回家）
SOLD CHEAPER THAN A SCOURING PAD
（比鬃刷便宜）
That may be true.
的確…
I might have been quite a brat for the first few years of grade school.
我在小學低年級是這副德性
But I became more girlie by the time I hit middle school.
但我升上國中就變得很有女人味了
See?
你們看
Wow!
哇
A picture of you and Takafumi.
是妳跟敬文的合照啊
-Let me take a picture of this. -A picture?
-讓我拍張照吧 -拍照？
FUNCTION - PLAY - DISPLAY - ZOOM
（功能，播放，資訊，縮放）
If you want, I can send it to your phone.
你想要的話，我可以傳檔案給你
-How? -I can email it or something.
-怎麼傳？ -用簡訊之類的
This phone doesn't have an in-box, and it can't call.
這支手機不能通話和傳簡訊哦
What?
咦？
How do you communicate with Takafumi without a working cell phone?
沒有手機的話，你要怎麼跟敬文聯絡？
I'm wondering if we can use smoke signals or flags.
不知道能不能用狼煙或旗幟…
Smoke is prohibited in an apartment building.
在集合住宅區用煙還是不好吧
Smoke signals and flags…
狼煙跟旗幟…
I didn't realize that this apartment was a medieval castle.
這裡是中古世紀的城寨嗎？
-What?
-咦？ -怎麼了？
Why is this coffee ridiculously delicious?
這咖啡超好喝耶
Can you tell?
喝得出來嗎？
I got 10,000 yen for my 20th birthday, so I bought a coffee mill and a bag of beans.
舅舅給我一萬元當作20歲生日禮物 我就買了咖啡機和咖啡豆
It's my first time tasting coffee brewed from freshly-ground beans. So distinct.
我第一次喝現磨現泡的咖啡 味道果然不一樣
Uncle gave you 10,000 yen in cash as your birthday gift?
生日禮物是一萬元現金？
How practical.
好實際哦
I had to.
因為…
I have no clue what youngsters want nowadays.
我完全不知道現在的年輕人想要什麼
Well, any gift is welcome if you put your heart into it.
不，用心思考過的禮物都很好
Really?
咦？
What if I got a GAME GEAR TV tuner?
那能接收電視訊號的 GAME GEAR組也可以嗎？
That's not a good gift.
不可以
CAN'T WATCH A THING (ANALOG BROADCAST ENDED IN 2011)
（看不到，類比廣播已於2011年終止）
Seriously, I appreciate cash.
我很感激收到現金哦
As there is still some money left, I'll get more beans.
那筆錢還有剩，我再去買些咖啡豆
I'll get some sweets then.
那我買些甜食吧
Birthday gift, huh?
生日禮物啊…
NEW MESSAGE
（新訊息）
A GIFT
（禮物）
FROM MY MIDDLE SCHOOL DAYS
（是我國中時哦）
How can I help you?
有什麼事嗎？
How to delete pictures on social media.
社群軟體、照片、刪除方式
Wait, why are you deleting it?
等等，為什麼要刪掉？
-This is what I found online… -Seriously, it's risky.
-已在網路上搜尋到… -這真的很危險耶
-…about deleting photos on social media. -What's risky about it?
-刪除社群軟體照片的資訊 -有什麼危險的？
You could get arrested and become ostracized by society.
被發現會死的，社會性死亡
You can get arrested for this? How frightening!
現在會因為這種東西就死掉嗎？
You can't.
沒那麼嚴重…
Actually, I'm not sure.
不對，很難說
Sorry, perhaps I was being hasty.
抱歉，是我太輕率了
Also, please don't show it to your uncle.
還有，別拿給舅舅看啦
THIS MONTH'S DEAL ETHIOPIAN COFFEE BEANS
（伊索比亞咖啡豆特賣）
Coffee beans are on sale today. I'm gonna go get a bag!
今天是咖啡豆打折的日子，我去買一下
What?
咦？
Fujimiya.
藤宮
Your swimsuit photo that you bet your life on…
妳豁出去的泳裝照…
lost to the sales ad for coffee beans in terms of content appeal.
吸引力輸給了咖啡豆特賣通知呢
No, no, no.
不…
I was just a middle schooler.
畢竟那張只是國中時的照片
If he were to see me now--
如果是現在的我…
Freeze!
冷卻吧
W-- What did you do?
你…做了…
I spilled my coffee! Did you get burned?
咖啡…妳有燙到嗎？
I can't use any healing spells.
我沒辦法用回復魔法
I feel like I'm frostbitten instead.
我反而覺得快凍傷了
Then…
那…
Spirit of fire,
火焰精靈啊
turn my enemy into cinder with scorching hellfire--
以灼熱業火將吾敵化為黑炭…
Enough with the magic!
不要再用魔法了
Please, feel free to take a shower.
妳去沖個熱水澡吧
I sincerely apologize.
真的很抱歉
You might feel uncomfortable showering while I'm here.
沖澡時我在家，妳會不自在吧
I'll be out for a couple of hours.
我會外出兩小時左右
I'll leave Takafumi's clothes out for you.
我會把敬文的衣服放在這裡
All warm and cozy.
暖和起來了
It's a men's shirt.
是男生襯衫啊
What if Takafumi's preference is girls in boys' shirts?
敬文看到會不會有感覺呢？
Who am I kidding?
不可能吧
Would he change his mind about me a bit if he were to see me in the nude?
讓他看到裸體的話 反應會不會比較不一樣？
-It won't hurt to be seen. -Uncle?
-被看到也不會少塊肉 -舅舅？
Why's the curtain closed?
你怎麼把浴簾…
S-- Sorry.
對…對不起
S-- Seriously, I'm so sorry!
真…真的非常抱歉
I'll be out for a couple of hours.
我會外出兩小時左右
-Takafumi. -I'm so sorry.
-敬文 -抱歉
I'm trying to shut out that kind of stuff.
我很努力讓自己別意識到這種事
But you are so cute, I can't help myself.
但妳很可愛，我忍不住就…
You must be uncomfortable, being gazed at in that way by a friend, right?
被朋友用這種眼光看待，感覺很差吧
Sorry.
對不起
If you could look at me in that way,
被你用這種眼光看待
actually, I'd be flattered.
我其實很開心哦
Fujimiya,
藤宮
you've been always so thoughtful.
妳從以前就很溫柔呢
-I'll take full responsibility. -Responsibility?
-我會負起責任的 -責任？
What do you mean?
你的意思是…
I placed the flag upside down.
我已經升起倒旗了
The flag?
倒旗？
What?
咦？
Takafumi, are you in danger?
敬文，發生什麼事？
You put the flag in emergency position!
旗幟變成緊急警報的狀態了
What is this?
什麼？
I used the flag to signal my uncle to come home.
我用旗幟聯絡舅舅，請他馬上回來
The spirits tell him the flag's position.
透過精靈的通知
DANGER - COME HOME - NORMAL
（危險，請回家，平時）
These guys were serious about flags and smoke signals.
你們說的狼煙跟旗幟是真的啊…
Uncle.
舅舅
I unintentionally saw my female friend changing clothes.
我不小心撞見女性朋友換衣服的場面
I want to be responsible.
我想負起責任
-Could you please erase my memory? -What!
-請你消除我的記憶 -什麼？
I see. Let's wipe it clean.
我知道了，我會徹底消除的
Spirit of memory, deliver unto oblivio--
記憶的精靈，將其帶往忘卻…
Stop!
快住手
Why would you do that, you idiot?
什麼消除記憶，你這傻瓜
I don't mind it at all!
我一點都不介意啦
Fujimiya.
藤宮
-Thank you. -Stop it!
-謝謝妳 -住口
You haven't changed a bit.
妳一點都沒變
You are so thoughtful.
還是那麼溫柔
Stop saying that! Stop trying to wrap this up!
給我住口，別想草草結束這件事
-Fujimiya… -Is this the new coffee bean bag?
-藤宮… -是新的咖啡豆
…you are being considerate to me despite being embarrassed.
妳為了我不惜犧牲自己…
Should I make coffee?
我來泡咖啡吧？
-I'll do it again if you erase it! -Fujimiya…
-要是你消除記憶，我就再做一次 -藤宮…
hasn't changed at all. She's a wonderful and a caring friend.
一如當年，是個重視友情的好人
-I'm so happy that we reconnected. -Dimwit!
-能跟她重逢真是太好了 -笨蛋
I hope she feels the same as I do.
要是她也這麼想就好了
LIGHT - DARKNESS - SWORD
（光，黑暗，劍）
HOROHORO PEACH 3% ALCOHOL
（酒精濃度3%）
Hey now.
喂…
Fujimiya, aren't you still underage?
藤宮，妳還未成年吧？
I turn 20 today so it's perfectly legal.
我今天滿20歲了，沒關係啦
Is that so? Happy birthday.
是嗎？生日快樂
Thank you so much.
謝謝
And you must be 34, as you'd been in the other world since you were 17.
舅舅17歲時到異世界，所以現在是34歲吧
Around thirty?
30前後？
No, my birthday passed so I'm actually 35.
不，我生日過了，所以已經35歲了
I see.
這樣啊
Around forty then.
40前後
"Around 30" and "around 40" are Japanese slang coined in 2006.
“30前後”與“40前後” 是2006年的新名詞
(VARIOUS THEORIES EXIST)
（定義上各有說法）
Shoot…
糟糕…
we don't have anything special for your birthday.
生日啊，我完全沒準備呢
No, no. Don't worry about it.
不…沒關係的
Well, then at least let me impart these words of wisdom.
那至少讓我送妳一句話吧
It's my life's philosophy.
這是我的座右銘
"A pinch is a chance."
“危機就是轉機”
When you are just about to give up,
覺得自己快不行時
when you are in a churn of negative external forces,
就像是負能量全集中到自己身上的狀態
you might be able to turn things around just by changing your focus.
但這種時候只要轉念 就能產生意外強大的逆轉之力
So no matter what adversity or compromised situation you face,
所以無論遭遇何種逆境、變得多狼狽
it's crucial that you fight to the very end.
努力掙扎到最後一刻非常重要
That was a long explanation, but I hope you never forget it.
雖然有點長 但如果妳能記住，我會很欣慰
I'm surprised to hear you impart wisdom.
原來你也會說這種話
Thank you so much.
謝謝你
"A pinch is a chance," huh?
危機就是轉機啊…
Sounds deep when a YouTuber who returned from another world says that.
從異世界歸來的YouTuber 講這種話特別有感呢
Flattery will get you nowhere.
什麼嘛，你這個傢伙
But now,
不過…
both of you have reached the legal drinking age.
你們兩個都已經能喝酒了
Icuras elran.
依丘拉絲愛爾蘭
This was the very first time I drank alcohol.
這是我人生第一次喝酒的時候
It was right after I turned 20.
應該也是剛滿20歲時
-You're 20 there?
-這是20歲？
That's right.
對啊
Everything I've shown you up until now was before this image,
之前給你們看的影像更舊
-so I was a teenager. -A teenager?
-所以是十幾歲 -十…
I was so young then. I've really aged.
當時真年輕，我老好多哦
-Yeah. -You're right.
-是… -是啊
He looks exactly the same as before!
完全沒變好嗎？
I can't tell how he's aged.
完全看不出哪裡不一樣
Wow, so pretty.
好漂亮哦
Wow…
哇…
Ms. Tsundere!
是傲嬌女孩
I guess she was there too.
這傢伙也在啊
I thought I remembered seeing her the next morning.
我以為是隔天早上才遇到她的
Is this pretty lady the one your uncle transformed into?
這位美女是舅舅之前易容的那個…
Yeah, she is his stalker.
對，她是舅舅的跟蹤狂
-Don't you mean the other way around? -No. I said that right.
-你說反了吧？ -不，我沒說錯
I don't know why, but she stalked him.
我也不知道為什麼
-Are you talking about Land Stalker? -Uncle, stay out of this.
-你們在聊《秘境魔寶》嗎？ -舅舅你別講話
What a coincidence.
真巧啊
Other tables are available--
還有其他空的座位…
What the hell was that the other day?
之前是怎麼回事？
You resealed the barrier above the city.
你重建了封印都市的結界吧？
Where did you learn to do that?
你在哪裡學會的？
Hey, try this.
這個請妳吃…
What is this? It's pretty good.
這是什麼？滿好吃的嘛
There are other dishes too.
還有其他料理…
It'd be great if you don't tell a soul that I broke the barrier.
如果妳能隱瞞我破壞結界的事 我會很感激的
-What? -Please don't tell anyone.
-什麼？ -請別說出去
How did you become so strong, orc face?
半獸人臉，你怎麼這麼強？
Because I worked hard and trained countless times… by myself.
因為我一直一個人反覆做戰鬥練習啊
That's not what I mean.
我不是指這個
Three years ago, when I first met you…
三年前第一次遇到你時…
you were obviously a novice fighter.
你不是以顯然沒受過訓練的身手
But you somehow managed to slay the venom dragon.
打倒了魔毒龍嗎？
I didn't know that was the venom dragon.
原來牠叫魔毒龍啊
Yes, it was. It was the venom dragon.
沒錯，牠就是魔毒龍
Did you fight without knowing what it was? With no weapons nor training?
你毫不知情、連裝備都沒有就去挑戰？
You'd have died in normal circumstances. You stupid orc face--
一般人可是會死的，愚蠢的半獸…
What was I supposed to do? I just wanted to save you.
沒辦法啊，我當下只想救妳嘛
Do you go around seducing other girls like that?
你該不會用同一招拐騙其他女孩吧？
When I slew the blaze dragon, the girl really appreciated me.
我打倒魔炎龍時，大家都很感謝我呢
The blaze dragon?
魔炎龍？
Did you use the god-freezing sword?
用凍神劍嗎？
Were you recognized as a torchbearer of the Ice clan?
冰之一族認同你是繼承人了？
-No. I defeated it without the sword. -You can't be serious.
-不，我沒用劍就打倒牠了 -騙人
The legendary blaze dragon is covered by magical blazing scales,
魔炎龍身上的龍鱗能阻絕所有攻擊
and you can only seal it with ice.
只有冰凍封印能打倒牠
No, you are wrong.
不對哦
A blaze for a blaze.
以炎攻炎
While the dragon is spitting fire, a physical sword can deal some damage.
牠噴出魔炎時 劍的物理攻擊可以稍微造成傷害
What? How did you figure that out?
什麼？你怎麼知道的？
I challenged it many times with different strategies.
就是不斷嘗試戰略…
You don't believe me?
妳不相信我嗎？
Here's the spoils from the battle. It's bottled blaze.
這是封印著戰利品魔炎的小瓶子
Open it, and the blaze dragon will come back to life.
它放出來的話，魔炎龍會復活哦
Seriously?
真的假的？
You can always kill it again.
你再打倒牠就好啦
Sir Orc has nothing to fear, right?
你不是無畏的半獸人大人嗎？
That's not true.
不對
The reason you can't beat it is because you've given up from the start.
妳一開始就認定自己贏不了 才無法打敗牠
What did you say?
你說什麼？
"A pinch is a chance."
危機就是轉機
What?
咦？
It's my motto.
這是我的座右銘
A single move may turn the tables even in the worst circumstances.
身陷危機時，一點改變或許就能逆轉勝
That's why you should never give up, and you should keep trying.
因此以絕不放棄的心態堅持下去 非常重要
Unexpectedly profound coming from you, orc face. Who said that first?
明明長得像半獸人…這話是誰說的？
Puyo Puyo's strategy guidebook.
《魔法氣泡》的攻略本
When playing Puyo Puyo, even when half the screen is gone,
玩《魔法氣泡》時，即使畫面都被填滿
don't give up and keep building.
只要不放棄思考
You might strike a huge combo and win big.
就有機會達成大量連鎖而逆轉勝
He learned life lessons from Puyo Puyo's strategy guidebook.
他從《魔法氣泡》攻略本 學到人生真理嗎…
I got tricked again.
我又被騙了
I've got an itch to play.
我有點想玩了呢
Do you want to play Puyo Puyo Sun on the SEGA SATURN?
來玩SEGA土星的《魔法氣泡3》吧？
When you get tired of sitting there, come join me.
是嗎？看膩了就來玩吧
Uncle is already moving on to the next thing.
舅舅已經看膩了嗎…
Are you busy after this?
妳等等有空嗎？
I booked a room at the inn. Why don't you come with me?
我在旅館訂了房間，要來嗎？
You think I'd follow you back to your place that easily?
哪有人聽你這麼說，還會傻傻跟去啊？
So you've shown your true colors, orc!
半獸人的本性終於…
Don't touch me.
放開我…
What?
咦？
Why?
為什麼？
-Let's go. -Okay.
-走吧 -嗯…
No, I didn't mean that.
不…等等…剛才是…
Uncle.
舅舅
Does he become an animal when he's drunk?
他喝醉就會變成肉食男嗎？
Can you guys join me for a round of Puyo Puyo--
你們還是來玩《魔法氣泡》…
We're fine! Go play a single-player game or something.
不用了啦，你自己玩單人遊戲吧
Here you are.
拿去
It's Burning Rangers.
是《烈火英豪》啊
It's not the same without a multi controller.
但我沒有圓形手把耶
You know how to handle him.
你還真瞭解他
Hey, you.
你…
W-- Walk straight.
好好走路啦
Thank you.
謝謝
I'm glad I have you to support me when things are rough.
難受的時候 有妳在身邊扶持，真是太好了
What?
咦？
You've been hiding your pain all along.
你一直都覺得很難受？
To be honest, it's been rough.
其實挺難受的
But I had you.
但因為有妳在…
The room is on the second floor.
我的房間在二樓
Okay.
嗯…
I didn't realize I meant so much to you.
原來我扶持著你的心靈…
Here.
就是這裡
Now, where's that key?
鑰匙在…
You are such a slouch! Fine then.
你真是不像樣，好吧
I guess I have no choice but to help you this way forever.
我以後也會一直…在一旁扶持著你哦
No. I'm good now.
不，到這裡就行了
You saved me! Being drunk is rough, all right!
得救了，喝醉了真的很難受
Thanks for helping me get back to my room. See you later!
謝謝妳扶我走到這裡，晚安
Takafumi, this game is much harder to play without a multi-controller.
敬文，沒有圓形手把果然很難玩
Did I fall asleep?
我睡了嗎？
-Yeah.
-對
Let's skip to the following morning.
快轉到隔天早上吧
My head is killing me.
頭好痛…
Hey, orc face, you sleepyhead.
半獸人臉，貪睡蟲
-What are we going to do today? -Why are you here?
-你今天要做什麼？ -妳怎麼會在這裡？
I'm going to try to clear the death trap dungeon.
我要闖蕩死亡陷阱迷宮
Talk about resilience. This girl!
她真的很有毅力耶
-Wait. Look at her eyes. -What?
-等等，她的眼角… -咦？
Nothing noteworthy… right?
沒什麼特別的事吧？
-Fujimiya? -I can't help but drink!
-藤宮？ -我怎麼能不喝呢？
Oh, I get it.
我懂
Here. You must drink too!
來，舅舅也喝
HEALING LEMON SOUR ALCOHOL 5%
（酒精濃度5%）
Uncle, you can stomach alcohol.
舅舅可以正常灌酒？
Of course, easy-peasy--
當然，輕鬆…
Shoot, I'm going to puke.
糟糕，我要吐了
-I'm going home. -Wait.
-我回去了 -等等
-You are the one who made him drunk. -Don't worry. I'll take you home.
-留下來善後 -瞭解，那我送妳回家
What? No, I'm okay. I don't live that far--
咦？不用了，我住很近…
Spirit of wind!
風精靈啊…
I'm so dizzy!
輕飄飄的
I can't fly well without a multi controller.
沒有圓形手把果然飛不好
Takafumi! Your uncle can't tell reality apart from video games!
敬文，舅舅分不清遊戲跟現實了啦
Uncle!
舅舅
My uncle couldn't hold his drink at all.
舅舅的酒量超級差
I told myself to never let him drink a strong sour again.
以後還是別勉強他喝 酒精含量比較高的酒好了
Let us down, Uncle!
快降落啦，舅舅
DEATH TRAP DUNGEON
（死亡陷阱迷宮）
Are you hurt? I told you not to follow me in here.
沒事吧？就叫妳別跟來了
Were you poisoned? Let me suck it out.
妳中毒了嗎？我要把毒吸出來
-Leave it alone. -How could I?
-別管我啦 -不行
You must be uncomfortable. I'll remove your armor.
妳很難受吧，我幫妳脫掉鎧甲
What?
咦？
You can leave the bottom part on!
下面不用脫啦
Are you okay? Does it hurt?
妳沒事吧？會痛嗎？
Is there anything I can do for you?
希望我幫妳做什麼嗎？
Could you please leave me alone?
暫時讓我一個人獨處好嗎？
Don't be dumb. I can't leave you in this weakened state.
笨蛋，妳這麼衰弱，怎麼能讓妳落單
Is the binding too tight around your belly?
是肚子不舒服嗎？
Orc face…
半獸人臉…
-Well… -What?
-你… -怎麼了？
-Sorry.
-抱歉 -啥？
More like an aphrodisiac in an adult manga than a poison.
這根本是中了A漫裡的春藥吧…
It actually exists.
原來那真的存在啊
Uncle, the screen cut out.
舅舅，畫面消失了耶
It's the effect of the Elf's hair accessory.
那是精靈髮飾的效果
We can't read the memory while it's in use.
戴上它就無法讀取記憶
She even used an item to hide the antidote.
她不惜祭出道具，也要隱瞞解毒方式
What a tightwad.
真是個小氣的傢伙
That ought to show you the danger of poison.
你們明白中毒的危險性了吧
Even that tough Elf almost died--
連強大的精靈都差點送命…
I want to poison Takafumi. Can I have a dose?
給我那種毒，我要拿來餵敬文
Why? Oh, you're so scary.
什麼？好可怕
Subtitle translation by: Naoka Matsumura
字幕翻譯：宋梅君